<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An alarum to pamphleteers, or, The danger of an habeas corpus being a serious and seasonable advice to anti-temporizing scriblers, to desist in time, lest they untimely be forc'd to sing their own obsequies, and write with their own pens in dismall characters their own epitaphs / by R.B.H.</title>
            <author>R. B. H.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H115A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R117</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13648453</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13648453</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43090)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 789:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An alarum to pamphleteers, or, The danger of an habeas corpus being a serious and seasonable advice to anti-temporizing scriblers, to desist in time, lest they untimely be forc'd to sing their own obsequies, and write with their own pens in dismall characters their own epitaphs / by R.B.H.</title>
                  <author>R. B. H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satire.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100957:1"/>
            <p>AN ALARUM TO PAMPHLETEERS; OR THE DANGER OF AN Habeas Corpus; BEING A <hi>ſerious</hi> and
<hi>ſeaſonable</hi> advice to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporizing <hi>Scriblers,</hi> to deſiſt in time, leaſt they untimely be forc'd to ſing their own Obſequies, and write with their own Pens in Diſmall Characters their own EPITAPHS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. B. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100957:2"/>
            <head>An Alarum to Pamphleteers; Or the danger of an <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O ſooner is the Sun ſet, and that Twi-light invades our Horizon, but the Owles that are pur-blind by light, flutter abroad, hooping in every Ivie-buſh. Whole legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Beerles hum and buz, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping conſort with croaking Froggs in Ditches: Thus it is, when there's a mutation in State Affairs, the Preſs preſently groans in the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth ſuch a numberleſs quantity of Spurious Paper Bratts, by which meanes Paper becomes to be exceſſive dear, and Gold finders quickly grow rich in the ſo often emptying of thoſe Privies, State biting or ſcurrulous Pamphlets dam up: But let them beware they imitate not too much the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Moths, that never leave flying about the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100957:2"/>till they have (at leaſt) ſcorcht their wings. I cannot but laugh when I think into what a deep ſilence and pannick fear, they'l be all thrown into when there ſhall be one of them caught, and for an example to the reſt ſhall be hanged up with his Pen, in his eare, as a demonſtration of his fault: As yet they multiply dayly, and fight ſtoutly in their <hi>Billingſgate</hi>-Language; ſome whereof ſhould they but ſee a Sword drawn, would be in a far more affrighted and amazed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, then the <hi>Indians</hi> were in, when they firſt heard the <hi>Spaniſh</hi>-Guns: Nay, I durſt ſay, That it would make ſome of them run to <hi>Pegg-Trantums</hi> and that's five miles beyond Hell, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as once looking behind them. They veriſie old <hi>Naſis</hi> verſe.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tutuis eſt igitur fictis contendere verbis.</l>
                  <l>Quam pugnare manu—</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis ſafer far to fight with words,</l>
                  <l>Then to contend with killing ſwords.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe fellowes now make it a matter of nothing, to ſpeak Treaſon in the Superlative degree, as firſt they muſt needs forſooth be medling with our Grave, Wiſe, and Gray-Headed Citizens, for taxing unworthily Alderman <hi>T.</hi> for having no beard, whereas it may be his Barbers fault: Grant it were not ſo, and that he never had any, what can he help it? <hi>Nam genus &amp; Barbam &amp; quae non fecimus ipſi,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100957:3"/>
            <q>Vix ea noſtra voce—</q>
            <p>And ſo likewiſe Alderman <hi>At.</hi> that leavs a ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſavour of piety behind him where ever he goes. And yet for all their high vaunring &amp; ſeditious words, would rather hang then act any ſuch thing really, and yet take the liberty upon them to reprehend-others for their dull, ſlaviſh, and unactive Spirits. But I ſmel their intent, they fooliſhly apprehend Treaſon is in faſhion, and that the Promoters of ſedition and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, are the onely perſons that are now regarded or eſteemed. And they forſooth muſt needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the number, men of the times, and are willing to venter the cracking of a Neck, rather then to want that which muſt procure Liquor to ſwill the Gullet: It ſeems they find this kind of libelling a ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney commodity, otherwiſe we ſhould not have half ſo many of them. Well I can reſemble theſe ſnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fellowes to nothing ſo properly as to Currs that (when they have no other object) will bark againſt the Moon, and retaining the ſame nature of the beaſt will bite at that ſtone that is thrown at them, though they indanger the breaking of their grinders.</p>
            <p>Alas poor Pigg-wiggen myrmidons, you muſt be Jocky like correctors, and conſers of every mans acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons without the indeavouring to reform your own. Yee are like the reſt of the wavering and giddy mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, whoſe ſmall ſpark of underſtanding being dimm'd and obſcured with the miſt of prejudice, and darkned with the Cloud of paſſionate affections, judge of matters and perſons, (that are ſo high they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em but very little to you) onely I ſay by your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100957:3"/>apprehenſion; And being not able of your ſelves to look into the debts of PARLIAMENTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY and ARMY politick deſigns and actions, then the ſuperficial bark will ſuffer the eye of your internal ſenſe to pierce into them, do by reaſon thereof even calumninate virtue it ſelf. Becauſe ſome high perſons now have been heretofore low; their ſtupid ſconces thinks no other, but they muſt needs have the ſame low minds and uncoath diſpoſitions ſtill. It is not what we have been, but what we are that ſhall ſpeak for us or againſt us. True worth may chance a long time to lurk under an obſcure cobling bulk, or under a dirty frock, and perhaps in the form of a ſecuring man, or elſe may be hid under a great heap of Thimbles and Bodkins, or ſome ſuch light things; but when goodneſs and virtue ſhall hack and hew their way through theſe impediments and obſcurities, you may then plainly ſee (as now we do) goodneſs, virtue, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, religion, and zealous, yet profound policy, ſhine as bright as the Sun in Velvit Jackets, though others indeed by ſome fatal neceſſity muſt eaſie be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, (ſince they cannot help it) to ſhine no brighter then the Sun, when he is eclipſed. If our Rulers were low, and are now riſen, it was by ſome meanes; if ſo, then teachly it may be by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per worth. But grant that the Devils temptations ſhould be ſo ſtrong, as to be poſſibly able to ſtaine their red white ſoules with any fault; what Man is there that dares come perſonally to delect or correct them? It may be who ſo e're thou art that durſt doe it, thou haſt faults of thine owne, as well as they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100957:4"/>and therefore can'ſt not be a convenient Perſon. For I ſhould think that the preſenting of Phyſick to a ſick Patient in an ugly and filthy forme and faſhion, may at leaſt occaſion diſtaſt in the Perſon, if not utter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall. For
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Good things looſe the grace of their goodneſſe, when they are not performed in that manner that is convenient, or when by good and convenient Perſons, they be not propounded. Wherefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it may not be ſaid of thee;</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Cladius accuſat Machos, Catalina Cothegum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>It is an excellent harmony paralell with that of the Spheres, to ſee a mutuall concent of workes and words, I ſpeak in generall; and that they walk hand in hand, accompanyed with verity and ſincerity, The Devill (you have heard) hath transform'd himſelfe into an Angell of light, for a time, but it would have argued a ſtrong deluſion, and very great folly to have then took him to be a Saint, or belonging to ſome holy order, but the Devill a Monk was he. Therefore I ſhould adviſe you not to look on things as they ſeeme to be, but as they really are. The Harpies have vultures talons, yet they have Virgin faces, why then may they not have innocent hearts; And as for the <hi>Hyaena,</hi> it hath continually the lookes of a friend, though it devoure like a face, and yet it may not prove ſo. Though perhaps our Governours ſeem like Watermen, that look one way and row the other; you muſt not therefore raſhly judge they will never arrive to their deſired and intended port. But you will object, and ſay that there are too many Scullers in one Boat, which by reaſons of their ſeverall opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100957:4"/>one going this way, the other that way, the third contrary to them both, and perhaps the fourth he knows not whither, the fifth it may be would do ſome thing, if he knew what. To which I anſwer, that by the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ltitude of counſell a Nation is oft times pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, for every ſingle Perſon cannot performe every act, but many together may doe — what may they doe? why — I forgot what I was going to ſay. But let me tell you what e're I think, that the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand of irreprovable wiſedome hath divided ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in all things into ſeverall perſons, and
'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to finde it epitomiz'd in one ſingle perſon. And therefore that man doth but manifeſt his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous arrogancy, that dares to challenge ſuper-excellency in the performance of all things; as did our P. Monarch K. C. take the P. which way you will, either Proud or Pious. He that will confidently give out that he is eminent in all things, doth thereby ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly inſinuate, that he is deficient in moſt things. But me thinks I hear ſome privately whiſpering, that had not our Common-wealths-men been ambitious, they would have reſted contented in their former ſtates and conditions. Suppoſe it to be true, what then? are they not here in moſt like the noble <hi>Romans,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing emulous of praiſe, and extraordinary ambitious, were thereby carried on to the effecting of thoſe things, that might be thought impoſſible for humane weakneſſe to attain to. Death though diſguiz'd in the moſt offrighting vizard, could never defer them from any high archievement, whither pious or impious. So that I ſhall think with <hi>Tacitus, Optimi qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100957:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>alteſſima cupiunt.</hi> To conclude glory, and wealth that they might inrich their poor friends, were the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubject of all their differences, and contentions. Why then ſhould we caſt an opproprium on our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, for that they are ſomewhat like ſo victorious and conquering Nation: I muſt not goe beyond the bonds of the Bookſellers preſcriptions, not to exceed one ſheet; wherefore to fill it up, I ſhall conclude with ſome few Queries on ſome new Books, though I intended to diſcant on them all.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whither he that wrote the 36. <hi>Queries,</hi> did not like a judicio is Aſſe, propound more in one hower, then all the <hi>Common-wealths-men</hi> could anſwer all their life time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whither a word to the purpoſe, or a Parthian Dart, may not be termed the Fooles bolt that is ſoon ſhot.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whither he that wrote the 44. <hi>Queries,</hi> is not more Foole then Knave, ſince there is ſeen in them ſo much of the firſt, but very little of the other.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whither the Inquirers will not 'ere long verifie the old Proverb, 'Tis good ſleeping in a whole skin, ſince.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, Whither he that tendred 19. Caſes for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> did not do prepoſterouſly and abſurd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſince all the World knows, that one little Caſe would have contained all that he ever had. I ſhould have added this
<hi>Querie,</hi> whither the Bookſeller that printed this ſheet, and my Selfe, have not more honeſty then we can tell what to doe with all.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
